I recently read about what the young generation of workers want
قرأت مؤخرًا عما يريده الجيل الأصغر من العاملين
in Harvard Business Review.
في مجلة (هارفارد بيزنس ريفيو).
One thing that stuck out to me was: don't just talk about impact,
بقى شيء معلق في ذهني: "لا تتكلم عن التاُثير فقط،
but make an impact.
لكن اصنع التأثير."
I'm a little bit older than you,
أنا أكبر منكم قليلًا،
maybe much older than you,
ربما أكبر منكم كثيرًا،
but this is exactly the same goal that I had when I was in college.
ولكن كان هذا هدفي تمامًا عندما كنت في الجامعة.
I wanted to make my own impact for those who live under injustice;
أردت أن يكون لي تأثيري الخاص لأجل الذين يعيشون تحت وطأة الظلم؛
it's the reason that I became a documentary journalist,
ولهذا السبب أصبحت صحفية وثائقية.
the reason I became
ولهذا السبب أصبحت
a prisoner in North Korea for 140 days.
أسيرة في كوريا الشمالية لمدة 140 يومًا.
It was March 17, 2009.
في 17 مارس عام 2009.
It is St. Patrick's Day for all of you,
يعرفه الجميع بيوم القديس بطرس،
but it was the day that turned my life upside down.
لكنه اليوم الذي قلب حياتي رأسًا على عقب.
My team and I were making a documentary about North Korean refugees
كنت وفريقي نصور فيلمًا وثائقيًا عن اللاجئين من كوريا الشمالية
living below human life in China.
الذين يعيشون حياة غير آدمية في الصين.
We were at the border.
كنا على الحدود.
It was our last day of filming.
وكان آخر يوم للتصوير.
There was no wire fence
لم يكن هناك أسلاك شائكة
or bars
أو قضبان
or sign to show that it is the border,
أو أي علامة تدل على أن هذه هي الحدود،
but this is a place that a lot of North Korean defectors use
لكنه مكان يستخدمه الكثير من الفارين من كوريا الشمالية
as an escape route.
كطريق للهروب.
It was still winter,
كان الفصل شتاءً
and the river was frozen.
والنهر متجمدًا.
When we were in the middle of the frozen river,
عندما كنا في منتصف النهر المتجمد،
we were filming about the condition of the cold weather
كنا نصور فيلمًا عن ظروف الطقس البارد
and the environment
والظروف البيئية
that North Koreans had to deal with
التي يواجهها الكوريون الشماليون
when they seek their freedom.
عند السعي وراء حريتهم.
And suddenly, one of my team members shouted,
وصرخ أحد أعضاء فريقي فجأة:
"Soldiers!"
"جنود!"
So I looked back,
لذا نظرت خلفي،
and there were two small soldiers in green uniforms with rifles,
وكان هناك جنديان صغيران يرتديان الزي الأخضر ويحملان البنادق،
chasing after us.
ويلحقان بنا.
We all ran as fast as we could.
ركضنا جميعًا بأسرع ما يمكننا.
I prayed that, please don't let them shoot my head.
ودعوت ألا يطلقوا النار على رأسي.
And I was thinking that,
وكنت أفكر،
if my feet are on Chinese soil,
إذا وصلت إلى الأراضي الصينية،
I'll be safe.
سأكون بأمان.
And I made it to Chinese soil.
ووصلت إلى الأراضي الصينية.
Then I saw my colleague Laura Ling fall on her knees.
ثم رأيت زميلتي (لورا لينغ) تقع على ركبتيها.
I didn't know what to do at that short moment,
لم أعلم ما الذي يتوجب علي فعله في تلك اللحظة القصيرة،
but I knew that I could not leave her alone there
لكني علمت أني لا أستطيع تركها وحيدة هناك
when she said, "Euna, I can't feel my legs."
عندما قالت: "يونا، لا أستطيع الشعور بقدمي."
In a flash, we were surrounded by these two Korean soldiers.
وفي لمح البصر حاصرنا الجنديان الكوريان.
They were not much bigger than us,
لم يكونا أكبر منا،
but they were determined to take us to their army base.
لكنهما أصرّا على أخذنا إلى قاعدتهما العسكرية.
I begged and yelled for any kind of help,
توسلت وصرخت لكل أنواع المساعدة،
hoping that someone would show up from China.
آملة أن يظهر أحدهم من الصين.
Here I was, being stubborn
وحاولت حينها المقاومة
towards a trained soldier with a gun.
ضد جندي مدرب يحمل بندقية.
I looked at his eyes.
نظرت في عينيه.
He was just a boy.
كان ولدًا فحسب.
At that moment, he raised his rifle to hit me,
رفع بندقيته في تلك اللحظة ليضربني،
but I saw that he was hesitating.
لكني رأيت أنه كان مترددًا.
His eyes were shaking,
كانت عيناه ترتجفان،
and his rifle was still up in the air.
وبندقيته ما زالت في الهواء.
So I shouted at him,
لذلك صرخت في وجهه قائلة:
"OK, OK, I'll walk with you."
"حسنًا حسنًا، سأذهب معك."
And I got up.
ونهضت.
When we arrived at their army base,
عندما وصلنا لقاعدتهما العسكرية،
my head was spinning with these worst-case scenarios,
كان رأسي ممتلئًا بأسوء التوقعات،
and my colleague's statement wasn't helping.
وكلام زميلتي لم يكن يساعد.
She said, "We are the enemy."
قالت: "نحن العدو."
She was right: we were the enemy.
كانت محقة، لقد كنا العدو.
And I was supposed to be frightened, too.
وكان من المفترض أن أكون مرتعبة أيضًا.
But I kept having these odd experiences.
لكني بقيت أواجه هذه المواقف الغريبة.
This time, an officer brought me his coat
هذه المرة، أعطاني أحد الضباط معطفه
to keep me warm,
ليبقيني دافئة،
because I lost my coat on the frozen river
لأني فقدت معطفي في النهر المتجمد
while battling with one of these soldiers.
في عراكي مع أحد الجنديين.
I will tell you what I mean by these odd experiences.
سأخبركم ما أعنيه بالمواقف الغريبة.
I grew up in South Korea.
ترعرت في كوريا الجنوبية.
To us, North Korea was always the enemy,
بالنسبة لنا، كانت كوريا الشمالية هي العدو دائمًا
even before I was born.
حتى قبل ولادتي.
South and North have been under armistice for 63 years,
وقّع الجنوب والشمال هدنة لمدة 63 عامًا،
since the end of the Korean War.
منذ نهاية الحرب الكورية.
And growing up in the South in the '80s and '90s,
وأثناء نمونا في الجنوب خلال الثمانينات والتسعينات
we were taught propaganda about North Korea.
روّجوا حملات دعائية عن كوريا الشمالية.
And we heard so many graphic stories,
وسمعنا الكثير من القصص المصورة،
such as, a little young boy being brutally killed
مثل قصة شاب صغير قُتل بوحشية
by North Korean spies just because he said,
على يد جواسيس كوريا الشمالية لأنه قال:
"I don't like communists."
"لا أحب الشيوعيين."
Or, I watched this cartoon series
وأيضًا شاهدت سلسلة أفلام متحركة
about a young South Korean boy defeating these fat, big, red pig,
عن طفل كوري جنوبي يهزم هذه الخنازير الحمراء السمينة،
which represented the North Koreans' first leader at the time.
التي تمثل أول قائد لكوريا الشمالية في تلك الفترة.
And the effect of hearing these horrible stories over and over
وتأثير سماع هذه القصص مرارًا وتكرارًا
instilled one word in a young mind:
هو ترسيخ لكلمة واحدة في عقول الشباب:
"enemy."
"العدو."
And I think at some point, I dehumanized them,
وأعتقد أني أنكرت إنسانيتهم في تلك اللحظة،
and the people of North Korea became equated
وأصبح سكان كوريا الشمالية متساوين
with the North Korean government.
مع حكومتهم.
Now, back to my detention.
والآن، سأعود لقصة الأسر.
It was the second day
كان يومي الثاني
of being in a cell.
في الزنزانة.
I had not slept since I was out at the border.
لم أنم منذ عبوري الحدود.
This young guard came to my cell
وأتى الحارس الشاب إلى زنزانتي
and offered me this small boiled egg
وقدم لي بيضة صغيرة مسلوقة
and said, "This will give you strength to keep going."
وقال: "سيعطيكِ هذا القوة للصمود."
Do you know what it is like,
أتعلمون ما هو شعور
receiving a small kindness in the enemy's hand?
تلقي اللطف من يدي العدو؟
Whenever they were kind to me, I thought the worst case
كلما كانوا لطفاء معي، اعتقدت أن الأمر الأسوء
was waiting for me after the kindness.
ينتظرني بعد كل هذه اللطف.
One officer noticed my nervousness.
لاحظ أحد الضباط توتري.
He said, "Did you think we were all these red pigs?"
قال: "هل اعتقدت أننا هذه الخنازير الحمراء؟"
referring to the cartoon that I just showed you.
مشيرًا إلى فيلم الكرتون الذي أريتكم إياه.
Every day was like a psychological battle.
كان كل يوم بمثابة معركة نفسية.
The interrogator had me sit at a table
كان المحقق يُجلسني على طاولة
six days a week
ستة أيام في الأسبوع
and had me writing down about my journey, my work,
ويجعلني أكتب عن رحلتي وعملي
over and over until I wrote down the confession that they wanted to hear.
مرارًا وتكرارًا حتى اعترفت لهم بما أرادوه.
After about three months of detention,
بعد ثلاثة أشهر في الأسر،
the North Korean court sentenced me
حكمت ضدي محكمة كورية شمالية
to 12 years in a labor camp.
بالسجن 12 سنة في معسكر أعمال شاقة.
So I was just sitting in my room to be transferred.
لذا كنت جالسة في غرفتي إلى أن يرحلوني.
At that time, I really had nothing else to do,
لم يكن لدي أي شيء أفعله حينها،
so I paid attention to these two female guards
لذا أوليت اهتمامي إلى حارستين
and listened to what they were talking about.
واستمعت إلى ما كانتا تتحدثان به.
Guard A was older,
كانت الحارسة الأولى أكبر سنًا،
and she studied English.
ودرست الإنجليزية.
She seemed like she came from an affluent family.
بدت كأنها من عائلة ثرية.
She often showed up with these colorful dresses,
وكانت تظهر غالبًا بملابس ملونة،
and then loved to show off.
وتحب التفاخر.
And Guard B was the younger one,
وكانت الحارسة الثانية أصغر سنًا،
and she was a really good singer.
وكانت مغنية جيدة.
She loved to sing Celine Dion's "My Heart Will Go On" --
كانت تحب غناء "سيمضي قلبي" لـ(سيلين ديون).
sometimes too much.
أحيانًا بشكل مفرط.
She knew just how to torture me without knowing.
لقد عرفت كيف تعذبني دون قصد.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And this girl spent a lot of time in the morning to put on makeup,
وأمضت هذه الفتاة الكثير من الوقت صباحًا في وضع مساحيق التجميل،
like you can see in any young girl's life.
كما قد ترون في حياة أي فتاة شابة.
And they loved to watch this Chinese drama,
وأحبت مشاهدة الدراما الصينية،
a better quality production.
إنتاج بجودة أفضل.
I remember Guard B said,
أتدكر كلام الحارسة الثانية،
"I can no longer watch our TV shows after watching this."
"لا يمكنني مشاهدة برامجنا التلفزيونية بعد مشاهدة هذا."
She got scolded
لقد تلقت التوبيخ
for degrading her own country's produced TV shows.
لإهانتها برامج بلدها.
Guard B had more of a free mind than Guard A,
تميزت الحارسة الثانية بحرية التفكير أكثر من الأولى،
and she often got scolded by Guard A whenever she expressed herself.
وكانت الحارسة الأولى توبخها كلما كانت تعبر عن ذاتها.
One day, they invited all these female colleagues --
ذات يوم، قامتا بدعوة كل زميلاتهما،
I don't know where they came from --
لا أعلم من أين أتين،
to where I was held,
لمكان احتجازي،
and they invited me
ودعونني
to their guard room
إلى غرفة الحراسة الخاصة بهم
and asked
وسألنني
if one-night stands really happen in the US.
فيما إذا كانت مواعدات الليلة الواحدة تحصل حقًا في الولايات المتحدة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is the country where young couples are not even allowed
هذه هي البلد حيث يُمنع الأزواج الشباب
to hold hands in public.
من إمساك أيديهم علنًا.
I had no idea where they had gotten this information,
لا أعرف من أين حصلن على مثل تلك المعلومة،
but they were shy and giggly even before I said anything.
لكنهن كن خجلات ويضحكن حتى قبل أن أتكلم.
I think we all forgot that I was their prisoner,
أعتقد أننا نسينا جميعًا أنني كنت أسيرتهن،
and it was like going back to my high school classroom again.
وكنت أشعر كأني عدت إلى صف الثانوية مجددًا.
And I learned that these girls also grew up watching a similar cartoon,
وعلمت أيضًا أن هؤلاء الفتيات كبرن وهن يشاهدن كرتونًا مشابهًا،
but just propaganda towards South Korea and the US.
لكنه حملة إعلامية ضد كوريا الجنوبية والولايات المتحدة.
I started to understand where these people's anger was coming from.
وبدأت أفهم من أين ينبع غضب هؤلاء الناس.
If these girls grew up learning that we are enemies,
إذا كبرت تلك الفتيات على معرفة أننا العدو،
it was just natural that they would hate us
فمن الطبيعي أن يكرهونا
just as I feared them.
كما كنت أخاف منهم.
But at that moment, we were all just girls
لكن في تلك اللحظة كنا مجرد فتيات
who shared the same interests,
يتشاركن الاهتمامات نفسها،
beyond our ideologies that separated us.
بغض النظر عن المذاهب التي فرقتنا.
I shared these stories with my boss at Current TV at the time
أخبرت تلك القصص لمديري في قناة (كورنت تي في) حينها
after I came home.
بعد عودتي.
His first reaction was,
كان أول انطباع له:
"Euna, have you heard of Stockholm Syndrome?"
"يونا، هل سمعت عن متلازمة ستوكهولم؟"
Yes, and I clearly remember
نعم، وأتذكر بوضوح
the feeling of fear
شعور الخوف
and being threatened,
من التعرض للتهديد،
and tension rising up between me and the interrogator
والتوتر الناشئ بيني وبين المحقق
when we talked about politics.
عندما تحدثنا عن السياسة.
There definitely was a wall that we couldn't climb over.
كان هناك بالتأكيد عائقًا لم نتمكن من تجاوزه.
But we were able to see each other as human beings
لكننا رأينا بعضنا بصفتنا بشرًا
when we talked about family,
عندما تكلمنا عن العائلة
everyday life,
والحياة اليومية
the importance of the future for our children.
وأهمية مستقبل أطفالنا.
It was about a month before I came home.
قبل شهر من عودتي،
I got really sick.
مرضتُ بشدة.
Guard B stopped by my room to say goodbye,
جاءت الحارسة الثانية إلى غرفتي لتوديعي،
because she was leaving the detention center.
لأنها كانت ستغادر المعتقل.
She made sure that no one watched us,
تأكدتْ من أنه لا يوجد أحد يراقبنا،
no one heard us,
أو يسمعنا،
and quietly said,
وقالت بهدوء:
"I hope you get better
"أتمنى أن تتحسّني
and go back to your family soon."
وتعودي إلى عائلتك قريبًأ."
It is these people --
كان هؤلاء الأشخاص،
the officer who brought me his coat,
الضابط الذي أعطاني معطفه،
the guard who offered me a boiled egg,
والحارس الذي قدم لي بيضة مسلوقة
these female guards who asked me about dating life in the US --
والحارسات اللاتي سألنني عن المواعدة في الولايات المتحدة،
they are the ones that I remember of North Korea:
هم الذين أتذكرهم عن كوريا الشمالية؛
humans just like us.
بشر مثلنا.
North Koreans and I were not ambassadors of our countries,
لم أكن أنا ولا الكوريين الشماليين نمثل سفراء بلادنا،
but I believe that we were representing
لكني أعتقد أننا كنا نمثل
the human race.
البشرية.
Now I'm back home and back to my life.
وها أنا الآن عدت لموطني ولحياتي.
The memory of these people has blurred as time has passed.
وتلاشت ذكرى هؤلاء الأشخاص مع مرور الوقت.
And I'm in this place
وأنا في هذا المكان
where I read and hear about North Korea provoking the US.
حيث أقرأ وأسمع عن استفزار كوريا الشمالية للولايات المتحدة.
I realized how easy it is
أدركت سهولة الأمر
to see them as an enemy again.
لرؤيتهم أعداء مرة أخرى.
But I have to keep reminding myself that when I was over there,
لكن علي أن أذكّر نفسي أنه عندما كنت هناك،
I was able to see humanity
استطعت رؤية الإنسانية
over hatred
تفوق الكراهية
in my enemy's eyes.
في عين عدوي.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)